Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen Memorabilia 5148 MB
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen Memorabilia
1868-1978
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen (ORC&B)
5148 MB
3.36 cubic feet
3.4 linear ft.
Memorabilia.
Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen Memorabilia including badges, buttons, push-pins, cuff links, constitution and by-laws, postcards, certificates, calendars and other miscellaneous items
5921214
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 23, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen (ORC & B) was founded in 1868 as an order of railroad conductors and later expanded to include brakemen.
The Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen was founded by T.J. "Tommie" Wright in 1868 in Amboy, Ill. as the Conductors Union. The name was changed to Order of Railway Conductors of America (ORC) in 1878. In 1942, the Order of Sleeping Car Conductors merged with ORC. The union's name was changed in 1954 to the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen. In 1969, the Order merged with the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and Switchmen's Union of North America to form the United Transportation Union.
The ORC & B International Headquarters, Grand Division, was located in Cedar Rapids, Iowa with subordinate divisions in the United States, Canada, and the Panama Canal Zone. The principal officers included the president, senior vice-president, general secretary-treasurer, executive vice-president, vice-president/Washington legislative representative, vice-president/National Railroad Adjustment Board, four regional vice-presidents, Board of Trustees (3 members), and the ORC & B Board of Directors (comprised of the above 13 officers.) General Adjustment Committees on each property (Class 1 railroads) were responsible for execution of the contract, with each chairman, as principal officer, exercising a high degree of autonomy. Legislative matters on the state level were the responsibility of the State Legislative Committee and its chairman.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5148: Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen Records 5148 P: Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen Photographs 6289: Order of Railway Conductors Division 642 Records
Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen -- Archives; Chicago Railroad --Archives; Chicago Railroad Fair --Archives; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen --Archives; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen -- Collectibles--Archives; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen. Grand Division--Archives; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen. St. John' Division--Archives; Pennsylvania Railroad --Archives; Southern Pacific Railroad Company --Archives
5921214
- ORC&B - badges, buttons, push-pins (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Badges - Two sided - 1) - "Galesburg, Division, No. 83, O.R.C., Galesburg, Ill." - 2) "In Memoriam"; "Order of Railway Conductors"; buttons - "Conductors, Brakemen, O.R.C.B."; push-pins - shaped like a railroad car with "ORCB"; round with "ORC"; rou
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Badges - All have a railroad car at the top and white satin ribbon attached. On the bottom they differ. One has a key and feather crossed. One has a gavel hanging from it. The last has a circle with a scales in the middle.
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Badges - All have green ribbon hanging from a gold/bronze pin, two have railroad cars on top. Two have nos. in the center of the ribbon [115] & [589]. The last has the initials "ORC"
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Badges - Brass with railroad car on top, red ribbon with lettering "Galesburg Division No. 83, O.R.C., Galesburg, Ill." with a feather and key hanging from bottom. Two are from "Galesburg Division No. 83" and are the double sided badges for "In Memoriam.
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Badges - All three have gold railroad cars at the top of a white satin ribbon. Two have gold scales hanging from the bottom. One badge has a gold sword hanging on the bottom.
- ORC&B - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Badge - Gold top "Welcome" with pendant hanging "To Oregon Division No. 31"ribbon has "11th Session of Grand Division L.A. to O.R.C.". Push-pin is shaped like a railroad car with "ORCB". Last piece is the pendant that goes on the bottom of a badge, shape
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Badges - First badge is 2 sided, one black, one colored. "Pacify Div., No. 267, O.R.C., Vancouver, B.C.". Second badge is only the ribbon portion, "Third Annual Salida, OW, 132, ORC, on Floor". Third is 2 sided on colored, one black for "In Memoriam". F
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Badges - All three have gold railroad cars at the top of a white satin ribbon. Two have gold swords hanging from the bottom. One badge has a gold crossed gavels hanging on the bottom.
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Badges - All three have gold railroad cars at the top of a white satin ribbon. First one has gold sword hanging from the bottom. Second badge has a tarnished circle with crossing gavels hanging from the bottom and "Galesburg Division No. 83, O.R.C., Gales
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Badges - All four have gold railroad cars at the top of a satin ribbon. First two have "267" lettering. Third badge has a gold sword hanging from the bottom. The fourth badge has silver circle with crossed gavels hanging on the bottom.
- ORC&B - badges (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Badges - All four have gold railroad cars at the top of a satin ribbon. First one has red ribbon with lettering "Laredo Division No. 399, O.R.C., Laredo, Texas" and crossed silver swords on the bottom. The rest have white ribbons with gold swords hanging
- Insurance analysis [contents from insurance booklet], 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Insurance analysis prepared by Fidelity Phenix Fire Insurance Co., Farm Engineering Dept., July, On property of Bermuda Plantation.
- ORC&B - key chain & cuff links (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Cuff links - shaped like railroad cars with lettering "ORCB". Key chain - gold with round pendant with raised railroad car and lettering "ORCB" on front, on back "ORC & B Centennial, June 1868-1968, 100 Years of Progress for Road Men"
- ORC&B - checks (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Eight checks written for various amounts to people and organizations. Saved from ORC&B's Accounting Dept. files.
- ORC&B - certificate of membership, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  "Certificate of Membership" for Wm Rush, from May
- ORC&B - constitution & by-laws, adopted May 12, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Book - "Constitution, Statutes, Rule of Order and Laws Governing the Mutual Benefit Department, the Accident Insurance Department, the Indemnity Association"
- ORC&B - emblem designs (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Sheet with the examples of 11 different ORC&B emblems to be used for different things.
- Gavel (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Gavel engraved for "Lookout Mt. Presented to ORC No. 402 by L.M. Cromer"
- Railroad passes, postcards and receipt books, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Receipt books from Div. 575 & 608. Railway pass from Southern Pacific RR. Postcards - "The Smallest Locomotive, Built in 1881 and still in service between Omaha neb. And manila Ia."; World's Fastest Locomotive, Pennsylvania RR's No. 7002 - Record 127.1 m
- Souvenirs - invitations, 1883-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Invitation from city of Cincinnati to Union to hold the Convention (1907); "Uniform Rank KOP Ball, Nickerson, Kansas" (Dec. 1892); Invitation to Union Masque Ball, Hutchinson, Kansas (January, 1883); Invitation to Ball, lists of committee members, Nick
- Souvenirs - booklets, 1868-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Booklets - "Fiftieth Annual Meeting, Centennial Celebration, Chicago"; "Program, 45th Grand Division, May 1954, Columbus, Ohio"; "History - Officers, Delegates, Program, 43rd Grand Division, Sept. 1946, Chicago"; "Souvenir, 39th Grand Division, ORC, St
- Railroad time card booklet, supplies and regalia catalogue (Box 2, Folder 4)
  "ORC Wahsatch Division No. 124, Time Card No. 15"; "Catalogue No. 23, Prices for supplies and regalia"
- Membership "Division Card" for divisions no. 421, 604 and 138 of the Order of the Railway Conductors and Brakemen (Box 2, Folder 5)
  "Order of Railway Conductors of America" and "Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen" membership cards
- Book of examples of 'Division Cards', 1889-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  "Order of Railway Conductors" sample of Division cards
- ORC&B ritual books (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Ritual books - "for use of Subordinate Divisions of the ORC"; "Burial Service"
- The Holy Bible - Conductor's Brotherhood, Elmira Division, No.9, 1876-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  "Holman's Edition" "The Holy Bible", c1876; [from cover] - "Conductor's Brotherhood, Elmira Division, No. 9, 1878"
- Conductor's banner (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Banner - White with yellow trim and tassels. ORC symbol in the center - circle with forearm and rope/forearm and lantern/hand and switch
- 2 Rail road flags, one red, one blue, used for signalling repair (Box 5)
  - Flags (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Two flags - one teal - one maroon [no markings on either]
- Certificates, calendar, etc. (Box 6)
  - Certificates, calendar, etc. (items found in mapcase 39 and badly in need of flattening) (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Original Copper Charter Plate - Order of Railway Conductors & Brakemen, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  made by Tru-Art Engravers, Cedar Rapids, Iowa, April, 1955 / Design by Karl Rittmann - Warwick, R. Island; 1st Printing (750) Lilly Printing, Cedar Rapids, Iowa, May, 1955 -- DO NOT DESTROY [this info/note written on the paper the plate was wrapped in]